A Finding Aid to the Ex Libris Records, 1973-2007, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Ex Libris records
1973-2007
Archives of American Art
Cohen, Arthur A. (Arthur Allen), 1928-1986
Cohen, Elaine Lustig, 1927-
Ex Libris (Firm)
AAA.exlibr
Archival Resource Key
2 Linear feet
The records of Ex Libris measure 2.0 linear feet and date from 1973-2007. Ex Libris was a New York City based antiquarian establishment that dealt in rare 20th century avant-garde books and periodicals, and was founded by Elaine Lustig Cohen and her husband Arthur A. Cohen. The records include professional files, sales records, printed material, and photographic material.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 4 series
Missing Title
Series 1: Professional Files, 1973-2007 (0.9 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Sales Records, 1979-1998 (0.1 linear foot; Box 1)
Series 3: Printed Material, 1973-circa 1991 (0.9 linear feet; Box 2)
Series 4: Photographic Material, circa 1980s (0.1 linear foot; Box 2)
Biographical / Historical
Ex Libris, a New York City based antiquarian establishment that dealt in rare 20th century avant-garde books, periodicals, and archives, operated from 1973-circa 2000, and was founded by Elaine Lustig Cohen (1927- ) and her husband Arthur A. Cohen (1928-1986). Elaine Lustig Cohen is a graphic designer, previously married to the graphic designer Alvin Lustig (1915-1955), who later married her long-time friend Arthur A. Cohen, a scholar, theologian, and author, in 1956.
The Cohen's began collecting avant-garde books and ephemera from antiquarian bookstores and artists in Europe. Ex Libris began when the couple amassed a surplus of material and Arthur placed an ad in the New York Times that said, "send for my list of Dada, Surrealist, Avant-Garde periodicals and ephemera." The inventory of Ex Libris grew to include other movements of modernism including Bauhaus, Futurism, Cubism, De Stijl, German Expressionism, Constructivism, and Fluxus.
Ex Libris published catalogs of their inventory, designed by Elaine, which were sent to libraries and museums all over the world. The catalogs are now collector's items. Exhibitions were organized at Ex Libris that complemented their inventory, and they often loaned material to be included in exhibitions elsewhere.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The records were donated in 2015 by Elaine Lustig Cohen, co-founder of Ex Libris.
Scope and Contents
TThe records of Ex Libris measure 2.0 linear feet and date from 1973-2007. Ex Libris was a New York City based antiquarian establishment that dealt in rare 20th century avant-garde books and periodicals, and was founded by Elaine Lustig Cohen and her husband Arthur A. Cohen. The records include professional files, sales records, printed material, and photographic material.
Related Materials
Also found in the Archives of American Art are the Elaine Lustig Cohen papers concerning Alvin Lustig, 1982, available on microfilm reel 2802.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Photographs; Futurism (Art); Dadaism; Surrealism; Bookstores -- New York (State)
- Professional Files, 1973-2007; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.9 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Professional files date from 1973-2007 and record Ex Libris's involvement with collectors, exhibitions, and works by specific artists. Items include correspondence, invoices, price lists, inventories, photographic material, exhibition brochures, and consignment and purchase agreements.
  - Bauhaus Textile, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bayer, Herbert, 1974-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bayer, Herbert, 1981-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - Bayer, Herbert, 1996-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Beinecke - Futurism, 1982-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Berman, Merrill, 1979-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bollinger, Hans, 1976-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Breitfeld, Alfredo - Pataphysical Archive, 1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Dada Purchases, 1973-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Dexel, Bernhard, 1983-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Fricke Antiquariat, 1980-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Fricke Antiquariat and Marzona, 1979-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Getty, Archival Resource Key (Box 1)
    - General, 1984-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Arnold Eagle and Hans Richter Archive, 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Huidobro Archive, 1995-2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - F. T. Marinetti Archive, 1992-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Barbara Rose Archive, 1993-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Russian Constructivism, 1985-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Holstein, Jurgen, 1974-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Kandinsky Manuscript, 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Kolodny, Frank, 1983-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Malburet, Martin, 1976-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Marinetti, 1984-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Marzona, 1981-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Modotti Exhibition, 1977-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Phillips, Elizabeth, 2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Pinto, Judy, 1995-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Schwarz Gallerie D'Arte, 1975-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Taguchi, Tatsuya, 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Vloemans, H. A., 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Zwort, Piet, 1983-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Zwort, Piet - Exhibition, 1980-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Sales Records, 1979-1998; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Sales records date from 1979-1998 and include invoices for purchased material.
  - Sales Records, 1979-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Sales Records, 1994-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Printed Material, 1973-circa 1991; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.9 Linear feet Box 2
  Printed material dates from 1973-circa 1991 and includes an article about Ex Libris, a bibliography of catalogs, exhibition announcements and lists, and inventory mailings. The majority of the printed material relates to Ex Libris's inventory and includes bulletins, catalogs, pamphlets, short lists, and special lists mailed to their collectors.
  - Article, "From Bauhaus to Their House", 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bibliography of Publications, circa 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Brochures, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bulletins, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Catalogs, Archival Resource Key (Box 2)
    - Numbers 1-5, 1974-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Numbers 3, 6, 9, 1975-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Numbers 10, 11, Bauhaus 11, 13, 16, 17, 1983-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1973-circa 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Essays by Arthur A. Cohen, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Exhibition Announcements, circa 1976-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Exhibition List, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Pamphlet Short Lists, 1978-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
  - Press Release, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Short Lists, 1973-circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
  - Special Lists, 1973-circa 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
- Photographic Material, circa 1980s; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 2
  Photographic material dates from circa 1980s and includes prints and negatives of inventory items.
  - Photographic Material, circa 1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)